So our game is really starting to take shape.
But before we move forward and as we keep developing, we need to ensure our code is always robust and
free of problems.
And sometimes you will only find these mistakes when they impact your game in some way.
But the more you program, the more you will understand how to keep your code clean.
But that said, let's take a look at our code and see where we can improve it.
So firstly looking at our tree sprite here we have this hard coded wait one second and that determines
the rate of how quickly our trees spawn in.
And if you remember from earlier, having hard coded values isn't always a good idea, especially if
we want to modify and upgrade our game in the future.
So instead of having this hard coded value, let's create a variable for it instead.
So let's just call this variable a spawn rate.
And we can move it into the wait one second input.
Now, as our spawn rate is set to zero, trees are just going to flood in.
But before we set this variable to a different value like before, let's create a sprite called variables
that we can use to control all our global variables.
So I'll just select a random sprite like this ball.
Rename it to variables and just delete all of its costumes.
Okay, now we can bring in a when start clicked, and then we can set our spawn rate variable to one
like so.
And if we hit play, you'll see it works.
So let's have a look to see where else we can improve.
So looking at our main player sprite, you will see that we never set the value of our movement direction
at the start of the game.
So basically you'll see that if we ski to the left, then stop the game and then start the game, our
player is still skiing to the left.
So we can fix this quickly by moving back to our variable sprite and setting our movement direction
to zero.
Yeah.
Fixed.
Now, the next thing you may have noticed is how our player sprite can move at crazy speeds left and
right, if we hold down for long enough.
So we need a way to limit the maximum movement speed.
So if we go to our player sprite, you will see this code here that if we click left or right, we just
constantly change movement direction by 1 or -1.
So we need to put a limit on this.
So here is a mini challenge for you.
Pause the video and try to see if you can stop this movement direction from getting too high.
Right.
Pause it now and see if you can figure that out.
So did you get it right?
Well, let's have a look how it could be done.
And remember, in programming, there are often a bunch of ways to do something.
So if you manage to solve this problem but your solution doesn't look the same as mine, that's not
an issue.
The key, however, is to have and find the simplest but most robust solution to problems.
So here where we say if left arrow clicked, I'm going to add another if condition that will check to
make sure that the value isn't too high before increasing it.
We can also add an if condition to the right error.
So now what we want to check is if the movement direction is greater than 18, which we will have be
our max speed.
And of course -18 will be our max speed and the other direction.
And check if the movement direction is less than -18.
Just like that.
And if we give this a play.
Well, that's not quite right.
And here we have a simple problem.
Basically, we are only allowing the player to use the arrows direction if they are moving at more than
18 or less than 18.
And we want it to be the opposite of this, ensuring players can't go faster than 18 or -18.
So simply all we need to do is go to the operators, grab this knot and stick them on each of these
if conditions.
Like that.
Now testing the game again.
All right, that works a lot better.
And now, before we close off this game, let's quickly add some functionality so that our trees spawn
at an increasing speed.
And to do this, we're going to use a quick and dirty solution, which is everything we have been trying
to fix in this lesson.
But this will help you see what bad code looks like.
And also we'll look at a much nicer solution in a future lesson.
So moving over to our variable sprite here, let's grab another Onstart.
And all we're going to do is grab a wait and then grab a set variable and change its input to spawn
rate, and then change the wait to 15 seconds.
Now for the dirty part.
Grab this block, hit duplicate, grab it again from the start, and duplicate it again and once more.
Now we're going to slowly lower the spawn rate, and we'll do this all the way until we get to 0.3 starting
from one.
Just like that.
So you can see that was quick and easy.
But as you are well aware, this is definitely not a dry code.
And we do repeat ourselves.
And this code is very cumbersome and it's hard to upgrade and maintain as you know.
So we'll look at a much better solution soon.
But for now, if we give this game a go.
Mm.
You'll notice that every 15 seconds our spawn rate slowly decreases and our trees start coming in faster.
Nice.